PALLAV K. JANI

(734)773-5755 • pkjani@ncsu.edu • linkedin.com/in/pallavjani

SUMMARY

Collaborative researcher with 4+ years of combined industrial and academic R&D experience in interfacial and surfactant science, rheology and tribology, test method development and surface characterization

<u>Experimental & Analytical Skills</u>: Rheological & tribological characterization of gels and coatings; Component interactions in polymeric formulations – isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC), quartz crystal microgravimetry (QCM); Goniometry; Electron microscopy; Confocal laser profilometry; FTIR spectroscopy; UV-vis spectroscopy

Computational Skills: MATLAB, Python, Origin, ImageJ, COMSOL

EDUCATION

North Carolina State University
Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Chemical Engineering
University of Michigan
Master of Science in Engineering (M.S.E), Chemical Engineering
Institute of Chemical Technology
Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.), Oils, Oleochemicals and Surfactants

Raleigh, NC expected December 2023 Ann Arbor, MI December 2018 Mumbai, India May 2017

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Researcher | North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC

September 2019 - present

Advisors: Saad Khan and Lilian Hsiao

Friction reduction by an amphiphilic slip additive on polymeric substrates

- Demonstrated adhesion and load-dominant friction dissipation modes of erucamide, an organic slip additive, on different stiff and soft substrates such as PP, LDPE and silicone elastomer
- Correlated friction reduction benefit of solid lubricant to the dissipation mode and materials properties of the polymer

Thermodynamics of epoxy-metal oxide adhesion in bisphenol A (BPA)-based epoxy can coating formulations (with Eastman)

- Identified molecular binding mechanism of epoxy resins with metal oxides (SnO₂, Al₂O₃ and Cr₂O₃) using ITC
- Established critical role of benzene rings of the epoxy resins in the entropy-driven binding to optimize adhesion

pH-dependent effects of component interactions in collagen-tannic acid formulations on hydrogel rheology

- Determined quantitative correlation between interaction enthalpy (ΔH) and hydrogel mechanical strength at different pHs
- Identified role of hydrogel hydration in weakening collagen-tannic acid interactions using QCM

Research Assistant | University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

October 2017 – April 2019

Advisors: Johannes Schwank, Galen Fisher and John Hoard

Anti-adhesive metal coating to mitigate low temperature (<250°C) turbocharger compressor coking (with Ford Motor Company)

- Developed sputtered thin transition metal coating to reduce low temperature turbocharger compressor coking by > 90%
- Optimized an oil aerosol testing apparatus at Ford R&D to simulate turbocharger deposits and screen metal coatings
- Designed and validated benchtop apparatus to simulate compressor flow conditions for testing coke-metal adhesion

Student Researcher | University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

January – December 2018

Advisors: Paul Zimmerman and Frank Reinhold (BASF)

Impact of shear on dirt removal in automated washing (Multidisciplinary Design Project with BASF)

- Designed lab-scale rotating dishwashing setup to quantify dirt removal under shear and implemented 2³ factorial DOE testing protocol
- Distinguished effect of non-ionic surfactant structure on detergency-driven and shear-driven dirt removal regimes

Undergraduate Researcher | Institute of Chemical Technology, Mumbai, India

November 2016 – April 2017

Advisor: Ravindra Kulkarni

Surfactant assisted co-precipitation to control nanoparticle morphology

- Examined the role of surfactant type on the morphology of synthesized nanoparticle precipitates using electron microscopy
- Optimized two precursor mixing strategies dilution and droplet mixing, to control nanoparticle shape

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Contact Physics & Tribology Intern | Corporate R&D, TE Connectivity, Harrisburg, PA

June – August 2022

Tribological investigations of surface coatings for stamping tool life improvement and EMI shielding

- Characterized dry and lubricated friction, wear analyses and identifies failure modes for 15+ coating formulations
- Developed performance rating matrix to down-select 2-3 promising coatings for product-level testing
- Collaborated with stakeholders from two different business units across three R&D projects

Product Development Intern | Ford Motor Company, Dearborn, MI

May - July 2019

Friction modeling in diesel engines to predict fuel economy benefits of friction reducing technologies

- Optimized and validated piston-ring friction simulation models in GT-Suite with field trial data for diesel engines with < 10% deviation
- Translated friction reduction of ring coatings and low viscosity oils into fuel economy benefits (0.6-1%) via modified fuel maps

Process Engineering Intern | Adani Wilmar Limited, Mundra, India

May - June 2016

- Identified key areas of oil loss (1.4%) by documentation of material flow of palm oil and palm oil-based products
- Proposed optimizations in pressure leaf filtration system to minimize oil loss and increase efficiency of oil refinery

SELECT PUBLICATIONS & CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

- Sarker, P.#, Jani, P.# et al. "Interacting Collagen and Tannic Acid particles: Uncovering pH-dependent Rheological and Thermodynamic Behaviors" J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2023, 650, 541-552 (#co-first author)
- Adhikari, P.#; **Jani, P.**# et al. "<u>Interfacial contributions in nanodiamond-reinforced polymeric fibers</u>" J. Phys. Chem. B **2021**, 125, 10312-10323 (#co-first author)
- Jani, P. et al. "Frictional shear stress dissipation in slip-induced solid lubricant using tribo-rheometry" The Society of Rheology 93rd Annual Meeting, PF9, 2022
- Jani, P. et al. "Binding interactions at the bisphenol A (BPA) epoxy coating metal oxide interface: An isothermal titration calorimetry study" American Chemical Society Spring Meeting, 3645016, 2022
- Jani, P.; Farias, B.; Khan, S. A. "Polymer microgels containing nanodiamonds: pH dependent component interactions and rheology" Bulletin of the American Physical Society, 66, 2021

LEADERSHIP AND OTHER ACTIVITES

Graduate Teaching Assistant | North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC

- Advanced Process Modeling (Fall 2020), Transport Phenomena (Spring 2021), Polymer Rheology (Spring 2022)
- Designed homework and examinations for graduate-level courses of process modeling and polymer rheology for 30+ students
- Conducted weekly office hours to assist and guide students through the course across three semesters

Graduate Student Member

American Institute of Chemical Engineers (AIChE), American Chemical Society (ACS), Society of Rheology (SoR)

Event Organizer | Sportsaga, Institute of Chemical Technology, Mumbai, India

• Supervised and coordinated a university-level cricket tournament comprising 16 teams across Mumbai (2014-2016)

AWARDS & PROPOSALS

- Contributed towards drafting successful research grant proposal on "biopolymer surface modification and biodegradability" sponsored by The Nonwovens Institute at North Carolina State University worth \$180K (2022)
- Best Overall Award' and 'Best Technical Award' for technical and presentation excellence at The Nonwovens Institute's Industry Advisory Board Meeting for research on solid lubricant surfactant coating interactions (2022-23)
- Graduate Student Association's Travel Award to support attendance at the ACS Spring Meeting (2022)
- 'Division of Soft Matter Meeting Grant' to support attendance at the American Physical Society Annual Meeting (2021)
- Provost's Doctoral Fellowship' and 'Graduate Merit Award' (2019-2020)